This is a really low car.
There's the lake.
So...
Okay, wait.
Yeah, so we go over there, right?
I'm guessing.
Yeah, okay.
Because this is the north side, right?
Cows.
It's not special.
No.
Well, he grew up himself.
I miss bliss.
Go back and get it.
Yeah.
Look at the size of that house.
Unless you have... 14 children?
Yeah.
It's an excess of family.
Well, that's an old house, but...
I think it's not basic.
I couldn't tell you.
Do you know?
Yeah.
This is Larry's house?
Oh, my God.
I guess this is the way, right?
Yeah.
I don't know what's in the wall.
What's that little thing?
Yeah, somebody's coming.
Oh.
In the house?
Oh, right, so that's number 31.
Let's see.
Okay.
Okay, so we go this way.
We don't have this anywhere.
Oh, well, it was down there.
You can get it on the way out.
There's probably a thing, right?
Hello.
It's official.
Who are we waiting for?
Anytime you're ready now.
I'm ready.
Okay.
So the way we start is
if you could just say your name,
how old you are,
where we are, and today's date.
My name is Larry Kramer.
We are in my study in my lover's
in my house in New Preston, Connecticut.
How old are you?
I'm 68.
Mazel Tov.
And what's today's date?
That I've lasted this long is
a major miracle.
And today is November?
15th.
2003.
Well, Larry, you know,
you've been interviewed
many times and you have a lot to say.
And what we really want to do are ask you
the questions that
you probably have not repeated ad nauseum
before and that maybe are more
of an internal conversation from people
who were inside ACT UP together.
So we're not gonna be asking you
these generic questions of things
that anyone
who's interested can find other places.
I just wanna ask you
a few background questions.
When did your family come to this country?
Well, my father was born in this country.
And his mother was from Russia.
and no one knows
where his father was from.
And my mother
came when she was four, also from Russia.
From Russia, okay.
When you were growing up, did your parents
participate in any kind
of politics or community activity?
Yes and no.
Throughout most of my, from
when I was about six till when I went away
to Yale, my mother ran a suburban chapter
of the American Red Cross.
She was called the home service director,
basically the second person in charge,
and dealt with taking care
of all the problems,
mostly having to do with the war
and servicemen and all fighting
and their families and things like that.
My father worked for the government
as a lawyer and was, I think,
probably quite puzzled
by the terrible things that were going on
in the government
through the 50s around him.
He had never done anything,
but he had friends who we all did.
People living across
the hall from us disappeared one night.
because the husband
had been named by McCarthy.
Kids in my school
suddenly weren't there anymore,
so I was surrounded by a lot of that.
Where did they go?
Where did they go when they disappeared?
Who knew?
The kid, I don't know if there was
a famous story about a man called Service
who was fired by I don't even remember
who was president then, Eisenhower
or somebody, for some presumed malfeasance
in the China department.
He just disappeared, and the kid
disappeared,
and the family disappeared with him.
They surfaced again at Harvard
and Radcliffe, I might add.
What was the name of the suburb?
Mount Rainier, Maryland.
It's just on the wrong side of,
it's in the wrong side of Washington
and what's Prince George's County,
which is pretty much black now.
Then it was exceedingly rural.
And it was the Prince George's County
chapter of the American Red Cross.
And that covered an enormous area,
almost to Baltimore,
from Washington to Baltimore.
And so she was always schlepping out
When I was a kid, I was taken to families
whose kids had rheumatic fever,
and I was put to work on the blood mobile
and all that sort of thing, which I loved.
Okay, so the community involvement
was really something
that your family emphasized.
Well, my mother was very much
a teacher and an exceedingly moral woman.
that it was our duty to help, yes.
And she was able to do it, and she took
a great deal of pride in her work.
Drove my father nuts.
So before GMHC,
had you ever been involved in
any kind of political organizing?
I would have to say no.
Okay.
Do you know why, thinking back?
Why I wasn't?
Yeah.
I don't think
it came from a lack of interest.
I think it came from a lack of ability.
I grew up late.
I was a late bloomer.
I was a very unhappy child.
I was a very unhappy teenager.
I tried to kill myself at Yale.
And it took a long time
to pull myself out of those troughs.
I went fairly quickly.
I was transferred to England to work for
Columbia Pictures there,
and that was probably what saved my life
in a way, because I was
able to be psychoanalyzed for
very little money,
and it was enormously helpful.
I wanted to write,
and I was terrified to write.
I was afraid to write, as so many writers,
young writers, wannabes are.
And through the analysis,
I was able to work through all of that.
And the first thing I really wrote was
my screenplay for Women in Love,
which turned out to give me
a certain amount of confidence.
So through the 60s,
when all the political shit was going down
in America, I was living in London.
That screenplay
was the first thing that you wrote?
Yes.
Now, how did you get that gig,
if you had never written anything before?
Oh, I worked in the film industry.
It was the first thing I wrote on my own.
I helped write a movie called
Here We Go Around the Mulberry Bush.
I worked in the film industry.
I was assistant to the president
of a bunch of First Columbia and then
United Artists, and my job
was to find writers and find stories
and find books for movies.
and work with young directors and all.
And London in the 60s
was the film capital of the world.
Hollywood was on the down map
and Rome had been the 50s
and the 60s and part of the 70s.
All the big movies came out of London.
And I worked for Columbia.
I worked with,
we were the king of the heap.
We made movies like Suddenly Last Summer,
and Bridge on the River Kwai,
and Lawrence of Arabia,
and Dr. Strangelove, and
Pumpkin Eater, and I mean, go on and on.
And it was just incredible.
So you just said, I want to write this,
and they said, okay, give the kid a break?
No, no, no, no.
What happened?
You're interested in all this?
Okay.
I mean, I'm just trying to understand
how your first assignment
could be something so...
Well, I wanted to write,
and I finally found out I could.
I basically wanted to produce movies.
And I worked in an office,
and how do you find money
to make movies and all these things?
In those days, there was no such thing
as video, and you couldn't make the kind
of movies that you could make today
for next
to no money that the kids can make.
You had to do it through a studio.
That was the only way.
You couldn't get
any kind of distribution any other way.
So part of my job was finding
young directors, and I found
a young director called Silvio Narzano.
who went on to direct Georgie Girl,
which was a big success,
which was sort of my package.
And in gratitude, he said, I have a book
I would like to make as a movie,
and I'll let you produce it.
You can go out and get the money.
And it was Women in Love.
That's basically how it happened.
And then it went on from there.
So you made a terrible movie.
It becomes involved
how we got to Ken Russell and all that.
But that's basically it.
Oh, I got it.
So then, okay, so when you,
and this was actually Jim's question,
and I think it's a really good one.
Since you had not really been involved in
political activity before, and especially
in the book Faggots, you have
a very critical view towards the social,
the way
that the gay community was constructed.
Still do.
What was it that made you think
that people should be accountable
and could be?
Well, Faggots has
a slightly different genesis
than Normal Heart and that AIDS.
I was very much in love with a man who
I now live with, but that was
17 years earlier, and I wanted
him to fall in
love with me, and he wouldn't.
He didn't.
Or he loved me,
but he wouldn't live with me.
And those were the days of extreme,
whatever you want to call it, hedonism.
I went out faggots as about a guy
coming back to America or coming into
the gay world, sort of naive
and inexperienced with that world.
Because there wasn't much
of a gay world in those days, remember.
It wasn't a community.
It wasn't a political community.
It was very little of all that.
It was exceedingly diffuse, dispersed.
And I went out to look at that world.
It was my shrink's idea.
Why don't you go out and explore what
the gay world is really like?
And that's what I found.
Most of the stuff, in one way
or another, happened to me.
And there are people
that are based on real people.
Not much made up, in fact.
That's not to say that one doesn't take
a certain amount of license.
And I wanted to know why our love affair
didn't work out, and I came to
this realization that there was,
that no love affair, no relationship
could withstand the baggage that
we were putting on it by having
so much sex with so many different people.
Who can exist through that
in a relationship
without one person or both going nuts?
So how could you expect that that group
of people, as you just defined them,
would be
able to meet the challenge of AIDS?
Sarah, that's a great, wonderful question.
But I did.
And I still do, and they still haven't.
I guess I felt...
It was a little different.
We were dying.
And it happened first, so far
as I could tell, to my people
around me, my friends, our group.
You just suddenly think, oh my God,
we've got to save our lives, I guess.
To this day, I don't understand why.
At its heyday, at its peak, hacked up,
how many do we have across the country?
10,000 people maybe?
With how many millions
of gay people in this country?
How did I expect it?
I didn't.
This is kind of a tough question,
but if you had never been involved in
fighting for anybody else,
where did you get the expectation
that other people should come
and make a stand for us?
I guess I never thought of it that way.
We needed help
and you had to scream for it
and I asked for it nicely originally.
We tried to be very nice to
the New York Times and to Ed Koch
and you learn very fast that you're
a faggot and it doesn't make
any difference that you went to Yale
and were assistant to the presidents
of a couple film companies
and that you had money.
You suddenly know what
it's like to feel Like a faggot
or a nigger or a kike, I did.
And I have said that, and I did.
And I remember the day it happened.
And I didn't like it, so...
I don't know if your question is...
I was always an angry kid.
My father and I fought like tigers.
Screamed at each other all the time.
I may have been unhappy
and I may have been shy, which I still am,
but I knew how to yell back at him.
And... I guess the one thing that
various analyses and working in AIDS
or whatever we were working in taught me
was how to make the anger
productive and creative and useful.
But I always had the anger,
so I think it was more that.
I don't know if I was I grew up
with a mother who was always dealing with
what was wrong with the system.
Why aren't
these people being taken care of?
Blah, blah, blah, blah.
She knew how to do it,
to go ask the system.
find money or something to get
somebody transferred, or money
for sick kids
in a house, or a burned-out family.
She knew how to do all that,
and she was confronting
the system all the time.
So I would, I guess, I don't think
that I was paying that much attention
to it, but perhaps I was.
Well, when did you first become
aware of direct action?
I think
we all made it up as we went along.
I don't know that we became aware of it.
There are all these terminologies
for these things now.
When did you first see people doing it?
The speech I made that night
in the center, I referred to this group
of Catholics that went up to Albany, 10
or 20,000 of them,
and screaming at the legislature there.
I said, why can't we do that?
I remember pictures
of the Vietnam thing and all that.
I don't deal in the... in the linguistics
of all this very well, either sexuality
or homosexuality or politics.
I was not a political person.
In London, the film world was filled with
Marxists when I worked there.
A lot of my friends were directors.
who all grew up with Marxist viewpoints.
And, you know, I didn't know
what the fuck they were talking about.
But you did know that you felt that...
Tony and I joke about it a lot.
You, and correct me if I'm wrong,
but the history, as I understand it,
is that you felt
that GMHC was ineffective.
You wanted to create
another kind of response.
So you must have had
an idea of another way of acting.
And I'm wondering where that came from.
GMHC was
an extraordinarily moving experience.
I've become very friendly
with Ana Oliveira, who's the head
of it now,
and we've become very good friends.
We had lunch the other day
and we were talking about various problems
that she's still confronting
and things that happen.
I've got to tell you, I started to cry
a couple of times during lunch.
Yet, I was locked in this vice there,
because I was surrounded with a board
of my friends that I had put on
that board, because my brother's law firm,
who still represents GMHC, drew up
this thing that we had for
tax exempt, and we had to have a board.
I turned to the guys I danced with
and put them on the board, including
Paul Popham, who was a close friend.
And they didn't like anything
of what I was doing.
When I would raise my voice,
when I would criticize
the mayor, very fast I did all that.
They didn't like it.
So it was hard.
It was hard.
And I couldn't push them.
I couldn't push them.
And I thought at one point I could.
I didn't even think when I had this, I
either go to that meeting
with the mayor or else I quit.
That's just Larry.
Larry's MO didn't think twice
about it didn't think it in advance
I'm gonna do this it just did
and then I couldn't believe it
when they said go so then began
these years in the wilderness from that
was like 83 84
before 87 I wrote normal heart and but I
Everybody was dying.
I mean, how could you not respond to
that in some sort of way?
Well, a lot of people didn't,
but I just couldn't believe
that that this country was so hateful.
So then you didn't come to
the ACT UP idea with...
Preconceived notions, no.
I didn't come to GMHC
with any preconceived notions either.
Direct action
was ACT UP's most effective tactic.
Where did that come in?
The big difference between Okay,
the big difference
between the two organizations was this.
I was determined
that whatever got started,
it would not be structured,
because that's what GMHC had become.
Everything had to have a job description
and approval by this and approval
by that, and I didn't want that.
So we went the other way.
I've often described it
as democratic to a fault.
And when people came and said,
we want to start this
or we want to start that, fine.
Because I remember GMHC
when I tried to get different groups
started, different people who came
and said, I can do epidemiology,
I can do—it was forever until we could get
a lawyer in there and do legal services.
People came to ACT UP and said,
we want to start—we were allowed to do it.
That was great.
There could have been more committees,
as far as I was concerned, as long
as they were focused on
this sort of thing.
I tried to steer it.
After a while, I didn't have any power
to do that, but you can influence things
and welcome things.
One thing I learned, the analogy
is really with the movie business.
I was trained in the movie business,
and you call it direct action,
I call it putting on a show.
One of the many things I learned in
the movie business is you get
so much more energy out of people
if you love them, if you thank them,
if you say, job well done.
I worked for a shit, my first boss
in the movie, a man called Mike Rackerts,
who wouldn't say thank you
if... if his life depended on it.
And I realized
how many people resent all that.
And I worked for film directors,
Ken Russell being one of them,
who would take his riding crop
and hit a camera person
or someone who was in the way.
And they hated him.
Why Women in Love is so good is
because I saw to it that that crew
was just nurtured
and loved every minute we possibly could.
Give them parties,
give them thank yous, whatever.
Remember their birthdays, take out
their wives, because Ken Russell
was such a shit to them.
And the movie is all there
on the screen because of a lot of that.
And I tried to do that at GMHC
in the beginning, but then when I came up
against my first job description,
what is a job description?
I didn't know
what the fuck a job description was.
Why do we have to have a job description?
Why can't we go get the best person?
And then became all this business about,
you know, you gotta have this person
and that person, and it's gotta be,
What do you mean,
this person and that person?
Well, you had to take people
whether they were good or not,
because they represented
certain genders or certain colors.
We didn't have
many women in the beginning.
The first paid employee
of GMHC was a black person, Phil Patrick.
We couldn't get black people there,
so somehow to have to have to deal with
all of that.
I always say, get the best person somehow,
and you get into
a lot of trouble with stuff like that.
No offense meant.
It's hard.
As I said,
we were making it up as we went along.
There were no rules.
There were no rules with GMHC
until we got all these job descriptions.
hey, it became the Red Cross,
and I'd had my Red Cross in my lifetime.
And I just, they wouldn't go after
anybody, they wouldn't criticize anybody,
they wouldn't picket,
they wouldn't protest,
any of those things.
But see, that's what I'm saying,
like picket, okay,
you wanted them to picket.
I mean, that's a direct action,
that's not like a bureaucratic service.
Well, I didn't know, it's trying to make
yourself heard, I guess.
Okay.
You call it direct action and act up.
Did you call it direct action
before you knew what direct action was?
Well, I mean, it's, you know,
there's a long history of that kind
of activity
for people trying to change the country.
Well, I didn't come from that at all.
I really didn't.
And I guess that surprises people.
So people just, so you just started ACT UP
and then people brought that with them.
I remember those meetings
where we would all sit around and talk.
The first action, which was, I don't,
I don't remember how it got to be
Wall Street, but We were in the room.
Were you there then?
I don't remember.
No, not the first meetings.
We were in the room,
and all right, what are we going to do?
We knew we had to do something public
because, because, because, I don't know,
because of the Catholics that marched on
Albany, I guess,
because there wasn't anything else to do.
How do you get attention?
And somebody said,
let's pick it, let's go against it.
Let's go against the FDA,
because they were
so slow in approving things.
There was a big to-do over
something called—I know that was
too early, but I had—Matilde said to me,
Dr. Crim, the big heavy
in all of this is Frank Young at the FDA.
So I sat down and I wrote an op-ed piece
for the Times, and they took it.
It's called
the FDA's Callous Response to AIDS.
Was it called AIDS?
No.
Yes, it was called to AIDS.
They took it, and it ran on the very day
that we had the demo, so we were
able to pass out
at Wall Street these flyers.
I had got Joe Papp to make an effigy
in the shop of the public of Frank Young,
and we hung him
an effigy out down there on Wall Street.
Where did it come from?
I think it just came from all of us
talking with each other all the time.
I don't know.
How did you get your piece in the Times?
Did you know people there?
Not like I know them now.
I have to say, I don't know.
I don't remember.
Well, let's get to ACT UP.
What were some of your concrete,
some of the concrete projects
that you worked on in ACT UP?
I like to think I was, I don't think
anybody did anything
specifically all by themselves.
I think that was the great thing
about it is that we worked as a group.
I tried to be like a den mother,
I think, more than anything.
If people started getting, there were
big disagreements between a lot of people
and I would try to smooth them down.
I don't know if you remember
the whole thing with Suzanne Phillips.
What was that?
I don't know.
She had a big fight with some other woman.
I've got it written down somewhere.
There were a lot of personality things.
If somebody had a great idea,
I'd just let
them know it was a great idea.
If I didn't like the idea,
I would try to say maybe we can work it
into a good idea, whatever.
It was a lot of behind-the-scenes
stuff, I think, more than anything.
trying to encourage people to remember in
the beginning nobody would work go on
a committee particularly
and trying to encourage people
to to join committees because committees
where I thought were so important
and that that was how the work
was going to get done and I used to go to
all the committees and Which committees
did you like to be part of?
Well, I became very attached,
as you know,
to treatment and data, mostly.
Iris Long was this incredible thing
that happened to ACT UP, just incredible.
You want to talk about the miracle
of grassroots organizing, This woman
just shows up one day,
this straight woman,
and after a few meetings, she gets up
and she says, you guys don't know shit,
in her nice way, and I'll teach you.
And she did, and she took two,
three people initially,
and then there were four or five,
and then there were bigger,
and she taught them everything they knew,
and then they branched out and met
other people, Boston
and at the NIH and all of that.
By the time, a few years later,
I would take Mark or to a meeting,
and they would think he was a doctor.
That was the amazing thing,
this incredible meeting where we were at
Bristol-Myers in some big office building,
and we were at a break in the John,
and the schmuck from Bristol-Myers,
we were pissing next to each other
in the men's room, and he looks over at me
and he says, that Harrington,
it is Dr. Harrington, isn't it?
And, you know, I just felt
he's one of my children, whatever, so...
So when you say you brought him
to a meeting, did you make
the contact with Crystal Myers?
Crystal Myers?
Who made what contact?
I don't know that anybody can remember
who made what contacts, basically.
There were people working on
specific drugs who, by that time,
who were dealing with representatives
in the drug company
and able to ask for specific meetings.
I was trotted out
to scare people by that time.
I remember another meeting at
Hoffman LaRoche, I remember a lot
of meetings at Hoffman LaRoche,
where the man next to me was shaking.
And I turned to the guy on the other side
who also, I said, what's wrong with him?
He said, he's scared of you.
And I thought, hey, wow.
Why do you think they were scared of you?
Because by then I'd had all
of this publicity
as the angriest gay man in the world.
Are you familiar with all that?
And fine.
I think I'm a pussycat.
And people would always say to me
after the interview, you're so soft-spoken
and so nice,
how come you've got this reputation?
Fine.
I'm in the movie business.
I know that that publicity of that image
was useful to act up and useful to me.
We could play good cop, bad cop.
And let them be scared of me.
Fine.
So you were the bad cop?
Whatever they wanted.
Who was the good cop?
Well, why...
The good cop were, the bad cops
were all the kids on the floor.
And the good cops were all the people
inside doing the negotiating.
That's what it boiled, in the end
that's what,
and that I learned in the movie business.
That's how every successful company
of any kind really works, is you got
a shit executive who fires everybody
or cuts everybody's budget, and you got
a saint executive who keeps everybody
happy and don't think they don't talk to
each other
at the end of the day to compare notes.
And that's basically what I think
I was trying to steer ACT UP toward.
Towards a dual strategy.
Yes.
I mean, there was a lot of flack
from people like Maxine about going inside
when we were finally able to go inside.
And I said, are you crazy?
Of course you go inside.
They let you inside.
What can you do on the outside?
You can only go so far on the outside.
Anyway, I'm convinced that the destruction
of ACT UP
was the severing of this dual nature.
What destroyed ACT UP is when treatment
and data picked up their marbles
and went somewhere else,
leaving only the bad guys, so to speak.
Why do you think that happened?
drunk on hubris, drunk on their brains,
drunk on the fact
that they were—the very things
Maxine predicted,
I might add—that they were
drunk on their power.
They could sit down with the head of
Bristol-Myers or the chief scientist,
or they could call all these people up,
and they could do it
on their own from then on.
They didn't need anyone
fighting on the outside for them.
Perhaps they even became
a little ashamed of us, I don't know.
But I will never forgive them for it.
I feel that strongly about it.
To this day, Mark
and I don't talk, haven't done for years.
But hadn't you yourself pretty much
separated from ACT UP before that?
I never separated.
I don't know where that came from.
Well, you stopped coming to
meetings at a certain point.
Only because I was writing
a play or I was sick or whatever.
I did do a play.
We had the longest run, I think,
of any grassroots organization
ever of success.
You have to pull back every once
in a while just
because you get burned out.
You get tired.
You couldn't disassociate yourself
from MacDuff.
It isn't like GMHC where they throw you
off the board or whatever.
Mind you, we wish we sometimes had
a mechanism for getting rid of people.
We had a number of people
who we should have gotten rid of
who stole money from us
and all that, but we didn't.
Larry, this may be a bad memory,
but I seem to remember one time you quit
because you wanted
ACT UP to have a president.
Did I make that up?
I think so.
You didn't bring in
a proposal about structuring?
A president, no.
Okay, sorry, excuse me for that then.
Oh, okay.
A president?
I remember you got angry
because you wanted
a certain kind of structure.
We can talk about that in a minute.
Okay, let's put in a new tape.
And to have to deal with that size
of a room got to be distressing
and boring for a lot of people too.
Because of the rotating nature
of the chairs,
People were constantly looking for
ways to make it all go smoother.
And we used to have meetings about that.
How can we make it go smoother?
How can we get rid of the bullshit?
How can we cut to the chase?
Whatever.
And there were a lot of ideas.
I don't think
a general was ever one of them.
I think at some point I got,
as things really got awful, I became
much more militant in thinking of,
in trying to, in visualizing,
act up as an army,
which didn't go down very well.
And I think at one point
I actually tried to interest people
in taking gun shooting practice.
Yes, I heard that speech.
You invoked the ear gun, actually.
I'll invoke anybody if it's useful.
But I believed it.
Tell me, let's talk about that.
Let's talk about that.
What was on your mind at that time?
Oh, who knows what was on my mind?
You have to be able to go back
to those times
and realize how totally everything was.
People would come up to, sick people,
guys would come up to me at meetings
and would beg me, isn't there anything?
Isn't anything out there for me?
Tell me what you know.
Who do I call?
You know everybody.
Blah, blah, blah.
What's coming?
Can I hold on?
All the time.
That's hard.
And we still, even
though we might have been inside
certain meetings,
we still really weren't inside.
This was in the days
when we weren't in there yet
and we didn't have the drugs yet.
The best demo
we ever had probably was at NIH.
No publicity.
Nobody picked it up.
There was a fire in Washington that day.
All the papers went to cover the fire.
That incredible show for nothing.
And it's like, as you as a playwright
will know, it's like
closing on opening night somehow.
All your work goes for naught.
So you get, you increase
the desperation quotient
inside yourself, I guess.
Did you take gun training?
No, but I would have.
My best friend is Roger McFarland,
who had been a Navy SEAL,
the equivalent of a Green Beret.
He'd had training in a lot of that stuff.
We used to fantasize about if the two
of us could somehow just go
and knock off people around the country.
Whoever, Jesse Helms.
People, enemies, basically.
Why do you think that nobody who died of
AIDS took anyone
with them from the other side?
Good question.
In this book I'm working on
now, it deals a lot with...
The American people?
Yes.
And it deals a lot
with this whole question with the Jews
and with gays not fighting for
their rights all through the years.
Almost everything that happened against
Jews in this country
happened against gays.
And in the world, I might add.
that you know it's all it's it's
it's history is written
that that henry ford was anti-semitic
and tried to get rid of the jews
it's not written that he hated gay people
and and and and did the same thing
for them the things that i'm discovering
would would would literally blow your mind
um there were concentration camps
in this country in this country
in the wilderness for black people,
for lesbians, for gay people.
I'm talking about
in the early part of the last century.
Rich people who didn't like them.
This country had mammoth, mammoth expanses
of land that nobody knew anything
about or how to find it.
And they would go and they'd put
100 black people in a camp that
they couldn't get out of
and let them starve to death.
Where was this?
Texas, Arkansas, places like that.
And who was organizing it?
Well, a lot
of them were Mormons, people like that.
And a lot of them were crazy people.
the stuff that I'm finding out
and the stuff that people are sending to
me now that they know I'm writing
this kind of a book
how I found out the Abraham Lincoln stuff
and it has the same
and I guess this is what I got from
my mother it has the same um effect on me
as how we were treated in the early days.
It's wrong.
It's just wrong.
And that makes me very angry,
that I can't walk down
the street holding David's hand is wrong.
That we can't have those 1,000 benefits
that straight couples
get when they're married is wrong.
And that's what motivates me.
And when that prick, I can't even remember
his name, Herb Rickman, who was
Koch's gay assistant, his gay assistant,
hung up
on me when I was trying to be nice.
We don't want to know about this.
A gay man working for a gay man,
telling a gay man
that this city would not help us, wrong.
You don't have to have political action.
You don't have to think in the kind
of terms that you're, the dialectics that
you're talking about
to know that it's wrong.
You're talking about a certain kind
of tribal relationship
that wherever gay people are,
wherever they're situated in
any power struggle, they should have
an accountability to each other.
Is that how you feel?
Well, that's how it came to feel.
In those days, I just thought,
you could die from this shit, too.
Whatever.
Yeah, I guess I got that
from being Jewish, tribal accountability.
We all stuck together.
I grew up in Washington,
not so many Jews there.
I was the only Jewish kid in a number
of my schools, or one
of a couple, until I got to high school.
I knew that we were
safer than other people to be with.
Yeah, good point.
I remember that feeling.
But do you operate that way yourself?
Like if a gay person calls you
and asks for help, do you?
Oh, God, yes.
This is mission control here.
And do you find that that ethic
has increased or diminished among
gay people now in this era?
I no longer talk about gay people
so much in terms of It ain't a community.
No.
Why do you say that?
It's a population, and community is
too small
and insular a word for what we are.
And that began to become
increasingly evident and act up
as we went along,
is that we couldn't support each other.
I want to get back to the inside-outside.
Who's that?
Could you just go up?
I just want to get back to,
you talked about one
of the most important structural ideas
in ACT UP, which was
the idea of an inside and an outside.
That there would be people sitting in
meetings with pharmaceutical companies
and government officials,
and then there'd be people
out on the street.
Well,
again, that was something that developed.
I don't think anything
from day one was calculated.
I've said it over and over again.
We made it up as we went along.
What were we being handed?
Excuse me.
Bless you.
What were we being handed that day?
What shit do we have to deal with?
And it was all new to us.
We didn't have experience in all of this.
We didn't come from all
of these political backgrounds
or service backgrounds or anything.
We were mostly you know,
white and privileged.
And there was a lot of flack against us
in the, quote, community because of that.
Backed up, yeah, a lot.
Same with GMHC.
There was tons of flack against GMHC early
on that we were all white boys.
Paul Popham and I used to go to
black churches and black organizations
trying to get them involved.
Didn't want to have anything
to do with it.
So yes, we were all white.
Anyway, we made it up as we went along.
It was all pro, whatever the word is,
reactive to what the government was doing,
or not doing, or doing in the city
and the state and the country.
There was plenty to deal with,
and how are you going to deal with
it with the limited resources we had?
All we had were voices.
All we had were a lot
of very creative people who could make
beautiful posters
and had big healthy lungs.
And because so many people
were sick, that gave us our spirit.
What the fuck?
They had nothing to do with it.
As the strategy naturally evolved,
what do you think determined
which group a person would end up in?
Sorry?
As this evolved,
what do you think would determine
which element, the insider
or the outsider, a member
of ACT UP would find themselves in?
I think we were all both
at some point or another.
I don't think it was black or white.
Peter Staley, who was certainly
a good cop, that was a bad cop,
locked himself inside Burroughs Welcome.
I got arrested plenty of times, too.
Do you think that all people
were involved in both aspects?
Again, it wasn't so black and white.
And it changed from day to day.
And it was a long time
before the good cops
could actually do anything.
We were all bad cops in the beginning.
And this is a bad terminology
because it connotes saintliness and devil.
And it wasn't that.
It was
just pressure versus honey or whatever.
You said that ACT UP was criticized from
the community for being white.
well, for being white, for being,
it became, as you well know, it became
a place to go where all the hot guys were,
in their black jeans
and their black boots.
It became a look,
and those were unfortunately
the people who were sick.
But enough of them came,
so that gave us the image.
There was a lot of criticism of that
by people who didn't look like that
or didn't want to look like
that or were older.
Older people felt unwelcome there
who probably wanted to do something.
There weren't
that many older men there or women.
And yes, there was criticism,
but it also gave us our image.
I think the most successful demonstration
in terms of what it accomplished for
us was the St. Patrick's Day thing.
I remember going to the meeting after it.
Everybody was terrified after it,
because it had been in the paper,
and every editorial page
in town had dumped on
us, and people were scared.
And I remember saying, are you crazy?
Are you crazy?
They're afraid of us now.
That's the best thing
that could ever have happened to us.
And it was true.
It was true.
And... Do you think that being an ACT UP
gave you personally
more access to the power system or less?
Oh, God, yes.
In what way?
I remember...
Oh, God, yes.
I don't...
I mean, it came slowly.
I remember...
When I was active in GMHC, I'd come home
and my answering machine would be
all full, 30, 40 messages or whatever
they could hold in those days.
The day I was thrown off the board
and I came home, zero messages.
Zero messages.
And I said, ho, ho, ho.
I had destroyed my soapbox.
And I had to remake it somehow, slowly.
Roger has a different view of all this.
He thinks I subconsciously wanted
that to happen so I could write
The Normal Heart, which I did.
And I think that's giving
a little too much power
to my creative unconscious.
I don't think it was that powerful.
What was your question?
Did you get
more access to power as a result of that?
Well, I come out
of the movie business, as I say.
And I learned very early
on the power of publicity.
And I always have felt
that the media was my friend.
I used to say this to people,
make friends of the reporters.
They may not be writing
what you want, but they can be useful.
I cannot tell you to this day
how I can call so many people
because we have become friends
over these years.
I learned that in the movie business.
I say to people who run not-for-profits,
why are you hiring communications people
from other not-for-profits?
Go to the movie business
and hire people from there.
They know how to get stuff in the paper
that's got an attention-getting device.
As I began to get more and more
of the publicity and had wrote more
and more of my op-ed pages and wrote
The Normal Heart and wrote Reports
on the Holocaust and all, then you become
sort of a, yes, people do call you
and you do have that access
and it has been sustaining.
Also a lot of everybody else is dead too,
so you get a lot of it by default.
Do you think
that you personally wanted the attention?
I don't look at it
or that or myself that way.
The whole thing about ACT UP is results.
That's all I was interested in.
I was not
interested in airy-fairy theories.
Results.
How do we get these fucking drugs?
That's what it was all about.
How do we get them?
And it was a slow process to getting them.
And if I had to go out there and yell at
somebody, I made myself able to do that.
Again, you may find it hard to believe,
but I am essentially a shy person.
And it became like
a Jekyll and Hyde thing.
And I took so much
of my energy from everyone else.
That gave it to me.
Could I do it by myself?
I've learned how to,
but originally it was hard.
Yes, it's given me—I can call people up
now, and yes, I can still get
an op-ed piece in if I want,
but it isn't necessarily transferable.
Case in point is
that I would like very much to be
an activist for organ transplant,
because I've been so lucky there.
Talk about
an issue nobody's interested in.
It's just like AIDS in the early days.
The numbers are nowhere comparable,
but the issue is just as bad.
Now I know the head of the op-ed page.
And I said, he actually called me,
would you like to write something?
I said,
yes, what do you want to write about?
I said, I would like to write
an organ transplant.
He said, oh, do something on AIDS.
I mean, that's what it comes down to.
It's very hard.
And again, the people who can be
your activists, by the time they know
they need to be
an activist, it's too late.
Okay,
let's just move on to some other things.
I'm thinking a lot about the trajectory
of the development of drugs, and I know
that you were very involved in that.
I remember, you know, there was a time
at the beginning when people put faith
in a lot of drugs that didn't pan out.
You know, dextran sulfate,
AL-721, all of that stuff.
And I even remember when you came in
and said, they're dancing in the streets
in San Francisco, compound Q.
When the protease inhibitors started to,
when the vision of protease inhibitors
came to be, did you know instinctively
that that was going to be successful
or were you concerned
that it was going to end up
like the previous wishes?
Oh, by the time the proteases come,
now you're talking about the late 90s.
Act up is all intents and purposes.
There's no more.
And I think, and to this day still think,
is that you... you hope for
the best and expect the worst.
That was something
that's always been my philosophy.
The days of AL-721 and all that,
I didn't think it was
so wrong to explore all these things.
And I don't want to say false hope is
better than no hope, but We didn't know
it was false hope, you know,
if AL-721 came out of
the Weizmann Institute,
for crying out loud.
you go with it.
Compound Q came out of San Francisco
and Marty Delaney, whom I'm still
very close to, and they believed in it.
And it did help.
Would you believe
there's still people on it?
And it did help some people.
I knew instinctively
from the beginning AZT was no good.
I did say that.
Was there a fight inside ACT UP about AZT?
No, what there was was about the dosing.
We were right, TND was right,
that they were giving too much.
I forgot they were giving, I don't know,
a thousand milligrams a day and really all
you needed was two
or three hundred, four at the most.
That was
because of ACT UP that that happened.
So I don't know, fights.
That wasn't within ACT UP.
It was
ACT UP versus probably by then the NIH.
I just want to ask you a little bit
about yourself as a person
with AIDS and the ACT UP context.
When did you begin to think
that you were positive?
At what point in all of this?
I theoretically still don't have AIDS.
I've never had a defining illness,
and I've never had low enough markers.
I am the luckiest man alive.
I never had to take
any HIV drugs until I got my liver.
And the only reason I had to take them was
because the transplant people
insisted to protect the liver.
They wanted to keep HIV in check
whether it was out of check or not.
So you've been HIV positive, asymptomatic?
Since 80, I forgot
when I was tested already, 85, 86.
And why do you think
you were asymptomatic?
I am lucky.
I have no idea.
Everybody, not everybody,
but almost everybody
I knew is dead from those years.
Do you think it's a strain issue
or do you think
it's a genetic predisposition?
I don't know.
You don't know how close I came to dying
a couple years ago
because of the hepatitis B in my liver.
I was given six months to live.
If you remember, I looked like this.
I had no energy.
They told me that was the end
because livers were not available.
And the days were ticking away.
Just prior to that, Dr. Fauci,
the man I had called a murderer
many years before,
has become one of my closest friends.
Talk about a moving story of irony.
He saw me somewhere
and he said, you look terrible.
And he put me in the NIH hospital
and they discovered a lot of this shit
that had not been discovered in me before.
And there was
a hepatitis B experimental drug
in trial there.
And so I got the, it was called a Defavir
and that calmed down my liver for a while.
But then it stopped calming down the liver
and that's
when I only had six months to live.
And I was down there one day
to pick up the medicine.
You had to go there once a month
to get the medicine.
And my doctor down there, a woman called
Judy Falloon, said, I think you may be
eligible for a liver transplant.
The minute she said that, I knew
I was going to get that fucking liver.
I just knew it.
She didn't say how I could get it.
She said I had to apply.
They were just beginning to transplant
people with HIV
and hep B co-infectants, we recall.
There was, in fact, an NIH trial out of
San Francisco with Michelle Rowland,
our old active lady
out there, putting it together.
wanted people like me.
So that's how I got the liver.
I didn't get it
because I was Larry Kramer.
I did it because they had this trial
that was just starting
and nobody wanted to go into it.
But now wait,
what year did you test positive?
Oh, that's a long time before.
I tested positive for HIV in,
I can't remember, 85,
86, 87, somewhere in there.
Before.
But I knew
I'd had hep B from the late 70s.
Then I knew.
At that era, a lot
of people were advocating for
early medication before symptom.
How did you resist that?
Because my doctor, Jeff Green,
said, I don't think you need it.
We had ordered Crixivan,
which was the first one out.
And I had the bottle in my hand,
and we were going to start.
And he called me up
and he said, let's wait a while.
I said, fine with me.
So what meds are you taking?
Which HIV meds are you taking?
I took...
I took AZT when my liver started going bad
and my platelets go down.
AZT, unknown to a lot of people,
also raises your platelets.
So I took it for that.
And then I took Epivir for 3TC,
whatever it's called, for the hep A.
And that's all
I took for a number of years.
And then when the transplant
started, I've taken a bunch of them.
I took... virus
up until I became resistant to it.
I took Sustiva, which I loathed,
until fortunately I became
resistant to it because it drove me nuts.
And now I'm on something called,
which is an amazing drug because it has
absolutely no side effects.
It's like taking an aspirin.
It's called Rayataz.
And only now they've just discovered
Steve Miles, the UCLA AIDS man,
has just discovered that Rayataz
interacting with the other drugs
I take is bad for hepatitis B.
So we know so much now, and I have
so many doctors that I I mean,
talk about patient empowerment.
I brought it to a new art.
I have six doctors
who get—I email everything about me,
and I pester them all to death.
And I take advantage of everything
I possibly can to get the information
I need,
just what we advocated everybody to do.
They don't like that I do
this group email, and not one
of them will, when they answer me,
will copy all the others out of courtesy.
They only send it to me,
and I've got to send it around.
Too many cooks, Larry, too many cooks.
Which of these drugs do you feel
exists as a consequence of ACT UP?
All of them.
I have no doubt in my mind
those fucking drugs
are out there because of ACT UP.
And that's
our greatest, greatest achievement.
Totally.
From that day, Iris Long came in
and started teaching the pharmacology
of everything, whatever was known,
or what little was known about the virus.
Through all of that.
We had guys
teaching us civil disobedience.
I don't know if you remember that.
We had some guy, some big black guy
who had done something
for Martin Luther King or something, came
and gave us civil disobedience lessons
about how to lie down in the street
and let your body go limp and all that.
All of those things.
We taught ourselves everything,
everything.
I didn't go to a meeting,
I didn't know what the NIH was until,
I don't know when it was,
After the Normal Heart, I think.
86, I don't know, a guy called
Tim Westmoreland, who was a wonderful man
who we owe a lot to, a gay man
who worked at the time for Senator Waxman,
who was the only guy
in government who was our friend.
And he said,
you really ought to go to visit.
Yeah, it was before the Normal Heart.
go and visit the NIH,
" and he set up this meeting for me there.
This was before Fauci was head of NIAID.
Oh, this famous story.
All the heads of the various institutes
can live in their own houses.
It looks like a college campus.
It's very pretty.
The head of NIAID was
a guy called Crousey, Richard Crousey.
And he invited us, invited me,
I was there by myself,
and my dog Molly, to dinner, to lunch.
And his assistant
was a guy called Jack Whitescarver.
And they gave me all this bullshit about,
you know, there was money for this
and money for that, and this is happening,
and blah, blah, blah, column A
and column B,
and I called them on everything.
And he had to leave,
and the dishes were all there.
So Jack White's carver
and I washed the dishes in this house.
And I had to go to the john.
And I went upstairs.
There was
only one john on the second floor.
And coming out of the john, I look into
this bedroom, and there are bookcases
and things and photos all around,
so what writer isn't nosy?
This one certainly is.
So I go in the bedroom,
and on Krause's bureau are pictures of him
with all these guys in bathing suits.
And I say,
holy fucking shit, this guy is gay.
And I go downstairs, and I say,
White's carer whispers to me, no one there
but him and me, he says, I want
you to know that my friend
and I just loved faggots.
So I looked him in the eye
and I said, Jack, is Krause gay?
No sound.
So once again,
we're crucified by our very own.
You've got Koch in New York City.
You've got Krause at the head
of the NIAID, which is
the most important institute at the NIH
for looking after infectious diseases.
And we've got this prick in
the White House who's got
a supposedly gay son
who— Do you still think he's gay?
Oh, I know he's gay.
All right, well then let's take
that paradigm
and let's move it to show business, okay?
Yes, okay.
So in terms of science and politics,
we have gay people who are telling
the truth about what gay people's lives
are like and who are uniting together
and who are changing the world
and saving their own lives.
And then you have gay people in positions
of enormous power
who are not at all dealing with
the reality
of what's happening with gay people.
Now let's put that
into the Hollywood arts representation
category.
Okay, your play The Normal Heart
is probably, and I know,
I'm just guessing this, but I think it is
the only work of art that actually shows
homophobic cruelty against gay people
that has been acclaimed
and made it into the mainstream.
Any other time gay people make that kind
of work, it remains underground.
And most of the representations
of gay life
and of AIDS really are predicated on
showing a certain kind
of heroic heterosexual who overcomes
their prejudices to benevolently help
the poor, alone, isolated gay people.
And if you look at most work
about gay people
and AIDS, there is no movement.
The story that you just told about ACT UP
creating the drugs that
you are taking today, that story is not
present in commercial representations
of AIDS and homosexuality, even
though many of those stories
are made by gay people themselves.
So how do you account for that?
How many millions of us are there?
Tell me, I don't know, 10, 20?
I believe
Jews walked into the gas chambers.
That's what I believe.
I believe they walked willingly
into their own destructions.
How did six million people do that?
I'm reading now so widely
into the literature of those times,
but they did, over
and over and over again.
Who walked them in?
Other Jews.
Mengele's chief right-hand surgeon
at Auschwitz was a Jew.
So why, so gay people
who misrepresent the reality of gay life.
Nobody took anybody with them.
Nobody, nobody, nobody to kill one person
was willing to kill or lose his own life.
So, but today we see so many gay people
involved in false representations
of homosexuality and AIDS.
Why are they doing it?
Do they know they're doing it?
I don't know.
You're cursed with
too perceptive a critical mind
in all of this.
People don't want to make waves.
I don't know.
Reports on the Holocaust is filled with
one essay after another
trying to understand why all of this goes
on, and in the end you have to throw up
your hands and say, I don't know.
I don't know why 10 million men
or 20 million men at the height
of the plague didn't fight to save
their own lives to this day.
And believe me, I told every one
of them, I was barred from Fire Island.
People stopped inviting me to parties.
To this day, I'm not on many social lists
in the gay world in New York.
Well, do you think that there's, okay,
but do you think that right now we're not
at the height of the AIDS crisis,
so the life and death issue
is constructed a bit differently.
So there's got to be something else
at stake.
Do you think that gay men just want
straight men's approval and they're
willing to tell
a story that isn't true to get it?
Or is it about money?
What is the motive?
I don't know.
I don't think they want
straight men's approval.
I think
people just don't want to make waves.
Leave me alone.
Life is hard enough.
I want to go home.
You know, straight people
don't want to do it either.
You show me
a movement that's any different.
a population that's any different.
Talk about some, I was, where was I,
at Harvard at the Kennedy School lecturing
a couple weeks ago,
and this beautiful reporter
from Kenya woman asked me, What message
did I have for her people
who were in such terrible straits?
It wasn't Kenya, it was somewhere else,
one of those countries.
I said, you're not going to like what
I have to say.
Get out there and do something.
Don't take it lying down.
Throw blood at somebody sit in
on somebody, close down
a hospital, throw, you know, whatever.
You have only yourself to fight for.
Why is everybody
so passive in all of this?
And I say it to gay people to this day.
I mean,
we still have this gay marriage thing.
I'm so sick of all of these people
who say, oh, I don't want to get married.
I don't believe in gay marriage
because I don't want to perpetuate
a straight blah, blah.
It's more pragmatic than that.
There are 1,003, or whatever the number is
that NGLTF or whatever it was then came up
with, benefits,
tangible financial benefits that
you get from the government if you are
married that straight people get.
And I now face all of that.
I have a lover I want to leave in
my estate, or he wants to leave me
his estate without whatever
the excruciating taxes are
that a straight couple
doesn't have to pay.
That's worth fighting for.
All these people who are adopting babies,
there are a lot of rights there
involved that we don't have.
So don't give me
that you don't want to perpetuate a
terrible heterosexual, whatever
it's called, ceremony or something.
You don't want to call it a wedding,
call it a, whatever,
just give me those rights.
Larry, I want to ask you.
Maybe we should change tapes.
Oh, you need to change tapes?
Okay.
Doesn't everybody talk like this?
No?
You know, as long as I've known you,
I've always responded the same way.
I agree with half of what you say,
sometimes within the sentence.
What don't you agree with?
That's not helpful.
I think that they're telling
straight people what straight people
want to hear about AIDS and homosexuality,
and I think they get rewarded for it.
People do, why are you oppositional
and other people go along with it?
It has something to do with
your psychology and development.
Okay.
All right, let's start with this.
Go Larry.
Okay.
Those reasons
are as good as any, I don't know.
I don't give
a shit what straight people think.
And I don't give a shit what
other gay people think for the most part.
And it's a lesson that I've, it's been
a hard lesson to learn not
to care what other people think.
It was probably one of the hardest lessons
I ever had to learn.
And I learned it long
before all of this started to happen.
But it's the best thing I ever learned.
I think that it is so hard to get anything
that you have created out there.
It is so hard to get a job, to get
a screenwriting job, to get anything
made, to get a book published.
And some of it has nothing to do with
the talent or the worth of the project.
It's just the nature of
how we've been condemned as a people.
And most people don't have the skills that
I have, that I've learned,
that I've taught, or that I've forged in
myself through all of this, to scream
and yell and kick and get attention
and call you names and whatever.
And they don't know how to do it.
And you have to do it from a position
of having nothing to lose.
which fortunately I'm in.
I don't have to worry about
making a living.
Very valuable gift
my brother gave me, exceedingly.
And I know that I've been lucky,
so I feel that's part of my responsibility
to honor all of that by doing all of this.
But people don't have that.
I hated Philadelphia.
I hated it.
And I said so in print, in an article
that was reprinted all over the country.
And I hated Ron Niswander
or whatever the guy's name who wrote it.
And I hated them all for making it.
And I loathed the movie.
But I come out of...
It'll just...
Are we going to hear the message?
Yes.
I don't know.
Why don't you just pick it up
and just say— You want to just pick it up?
Who is it, and can I call you back?
Hello?
No, can I take a message?
Who's calling?
I'm being interviewed.
It's David Webster.
Yeah, tell him I'm being interviewed.
What's up?
We're in the middle of an interview.
He wants to know what's up.
Being filmed.
Relating this to Larry.
Yes.
Did you get something for the people
that you were going to dinner with?
No.
Okay, we'll see you later.
Okay.
There you go.
What do you think would have to change for
the-
I just know how hard it is for them.
I, like all the rest of us, went after
Barry Diller and David Geffen
and all these people
in the movie business forever.
And did they change?
David Geffen did, Barry Diller didn't.
Well, if the true story of AIDS is
that gay people were despised
and abandoned, and people with AIDS
and gay people and some straight women
like Iris Long united together
and built a movement and were brilliant
and changed the world and saved
their own lives, if that is the story,
how long will it take before
that story gets told in a mainstream way?
Somebody's got to write it.
Do you think that the... Go ahead.
I...
I'm writing a certain amount
of it, but not that specific.
Nobody's written about it.
I got Mark Harrington a book deal
after the fast track thing was fashioned
because of us, when we were still talking.
He wrote the book.
And it was never published.
I was never given the opportunity
to read it
because by then we'd stopped talking.
So I don't know if it was any good,
but it was indeed about the mechanism
of all of this
and how we had fought through all of this.
Do you think that the culture
is ready to face the truth of that story?
I don't think people give a shit about us.
You talk about
it as if they're doing it intentionally.
Some of them are.
You know, the Jesse Helmses
and the right-wing blah-blahs are.
But most people really don't care.
It's
like I don't give a shit about football.
And I'm sure a lot of people,
I have
a lot of gay friends who love football.
But I mean, talk about
something that puts me to sleep.
And if we're at all lucky, it's
because enough people have come out
and enough gay sons have died or whatever,
so parents are more, and younger people
are more accepting of their gay friends
and things are a little better
in the schools and all that,
and that's just an evolutionary thing.
But you want to put people to sleep fast,
just say, the things that you're saying.
I believe in conspiracies as much
as the next person, and I think
that there are plenty
of those around against us particularly.
My book is a history
of conspiracies, of hate against us.
There's no shortage of them.
What there is a shortage is of
people getting up and fighting back.
And that's what you're talking about.
And to this day, I do not know
why people don't fight back.
And I go back to this Jews
walking into the gas chambers analogy.
They did.
I know I wouldn't have, I think.
But an awful lot of them sure did.
Is your new book a novel?
I don't know what to call it.
It was originally just called
The American People.
Now I call it
The American People, a history.
An awful lot of it is true.
And a lot of it is fictionalized only
for legal reasons.
And some of it is out and out fiction.
But a lot of it is true.
So I don't know.
I would say over half of it is true.
Are there characters?
Oh, God, yes.
Thousands.
Cast of thousands.
And is it truly, I mean, I've heard rumors
that it's thousands of pages.
It's 3,000 at this point.
3,000 pages.
And they love it.
My editor loves it.
He doesn't want it shorter.
So when is it coming?
When it's finished.
So Larry, do you think
that you are taken seriously as an artist?
No.
Why?
Because I'm an activist.
And so what
does that do in people's minds?
I know I am not
a part of the literary gay lit mafia
and I know that I'm not respected
and I know I've been ostracized in
many ways and when there's a list
of a hundred best gay this
and that put out
by gay people, I'm never on it.
And what do you think the reason is?
I think it's because I'm an activist
and I'm known as this activist person
and this is not a country
where where political involvement
by creative artists
is—I don't like to call myself an artist,
but you know what
I mean—by creative people is respected.
It's not like I identify far more with,
you know, with German writers like Boll
and Grass and and Sebold and
South American writers
who write about it as a matter of course.
Part of my fury at the gay writers
has been over just this,
that in the height of AIDS, the people
like David Levitt and Ed White
continue to write books that are nothing
about which are about nothing but fucking.
And I'm sorry.
I'm about more than my cock.
And that makes a lot of people angry.
That's a whole other conversation.
But that's
why I'm ostracized, and it's fine.
I can deal with it.
I don't want to be their friend.
Okay.
I have a couple of other questions,
and then I think we're coming to an end.
Oh, I like this.
You're 68 years old,
and you've been living with
HIV for about 20 years.
You've survived a liver transplant.
Basically,
you're having a normal lifespan.
That must be shocking on some level.
I never take anything for granted.
Was there a moment when you realized,
wow, I'm having a full life?
I don't let myself think that way.
I remember coming out of the transplant,
out of ICU, and you never saw
anybody bound into the hospital
with so much excitement as
when they called me for my liver.
And I was there with my lover David
and Roger, and it was Christmas time,
and they had both gone back to New York,
and I was still in Pittsburgh,
and I had taken a sleeping pill.
The call came in at 11 o'clock at night,
get to the hospital as soon as possible.
Getting a taxi in Pittsburgh is real hard.
Somehow they got me there,
and I rushed into the hospital.
I said, let's go, let's go, let's go.
And the guy looked at me
and said, are you crazy?
Do you know
what is about to happen to you?
And I said,
I've been waiting for this a long time.
And when I came out of the fog
I was in, you do a lot of thinking.
Why me?
How did I live through all of this?
And everybody else said,
you think a lot about that.
And it's like, why didn't everybody fight?
I don't know.
That's one of those.
You can think about it
and you can make all kinds of promises.
I don't happen to believe in
God, so you can't.
deal with it on that level.
And I haven't done since I was like 13.
But you wonder, you think,
can't help but do that to you.
I don't take anything for granted.
The drugs for so many years
have been Uncomfortable, so you never...
This is the last six months or so,
three months since I've been on
these new drugs, this is the last time
I've actually felt human
without having to deal with side effects
like diarrhea or constipation
or whatever, and lack of energy.
Dr. Fung, my surgeon, said,
in all seriousness,
that I should easily have
another 20 years.
I also have liver of a 45-year-old man,
and he said with all seriousness,
you are as old
as your liver, so I'll take that too.
But there's not a day
where I don't worry about
something going wrong.
We don't know what these medicines do for
you that we unleashed on the world.
Every single one of them is found to have
so many different side effects
and so many different kinds of people
that you can never take anything
for granted.
This wonderful regimen that
everybody dreamed up for me
three weeks, three months ago.
Another doctor has just come forth
and discovered something
that may be bad for me particularly.
So it's hard because all the,
you have to bet, you have to do
different form of kinetics
between the HIV drug
and the anti-rejection drug.
And that takes a long time to balance
the amount
of the program it's called in your blood.
How much does your health care cost
per year, just out of curiosity?
Well, that's a whole other issue.
My liver transplant
costs Medicare $500,000.
I sold the bill.
I take one medicine a month.
I get an infusion of something
called hepatitis B immune globulin.
It costs $8,000 a month.
And every time you go into the clinic
at Pittsburgh, there's always somebody
who is either waiting there to waylay
a doctor to grab his leg and say, please,
please, please, please take me
when they've been rejected for a liver,
or somebody there who is The whole town
has sold everything, literally.
The whole town has sold everything
so that they can be there.
When I was there, I got accepted by
Medicare and that Belinda,
black AIDS activist from Boston,
was turned down by Medicare.
Same situation.
And unfortunately, she raised the money,
but unfortunately,
she didn't survive the transplant.
So I have been
very lucky all along the line.
I didn't need the AIDS drugs.
When I needed a Hep B drug,
it suddenly was there
in an experimental trial.
When I needed a liver,
it was suddenly there, timing.
I mean, I'm exceedingly grateful.
That's why I work so hard on the book,
because that's my, if I've been spared,
I think it's been
because I'm here to tell this story.
I'm the only gay writer who was on
the front line, that's still alive,
who was on
the front line from the very beginning.
And I know where all the bodies
are buried,
figuratively and metaphorically.
No, actually and metaphorically, anyway.
And that's what propels me every day.
Seven days a week I write.
That's why I'm up here.
Okay.
Just one last thing.
At the beginning of the interview,
you were talking about discovering
the level of, cruelty
and difference towards gay people.
You said they didn't care that you went to
Yale, they didn't care
if you had money, you were just a faggot.
Do you think that that's still true?
Oh, God, yes.
That they don't care that you went to
Yale and that you have money?
You don't think that makes a difference?
Well,
it depends what you're talking about.
Has that... Doesn't make any difference
to Gary Bauer, doesn't make
any difference to George Bush.
But in the years...
Who went to Yale too.
Okay, but in those years
since you started with GMHC to now,
do those two factors, do they,
have they changed in terms of your ability
to be seen by other people?
Oh, of course.
I mean, things have changed
and one should never deny
that they haven't.
You're either a cup-half-full person
or a cup-half-empty person,
and I'm half-empty, I guess.
I spent over 20 years trying to get
Yale to teach gay studies,
offering them money all along the line,
and was turned down
and was treated terribly, just terribly.
Why did they turn you down?
What is the real story?
We don't want to, we don't believe in
isolating populations
by themselves, separating them.
And I said, well, you got women's studies,
and you got black studies,
and you got Chinese studies.
Why can't we have gay studies?
And they have, well,
we don't think it's a discipline yet.
We haven't earned
the right to be a discipline or whatever.
Well, give us a chance.
I mean, it was awful.
And of course, Was this for gay
and lesbian studies
or for gay male studies?
No, that became a whole issue
that got way out
in my will, which I had sent to them.
I specified all kinds of courses
that could be given for men
and for women, and I separated them.
Lesbian literature, gay male literature.
And for whatever reason, when the Times
ran the story,
they only made the gay male literature.
So lesbians got up in arms,
quite understandably, especially at Yale,
that I was only interested in that.
But that wasn't true.
Anyway, they didn't want me.
They didn't want the money.
And of course, the only me they knew
was this angriest gay man in the world.
So that did not go down well,
and they didn't treat me well.
And it was only, again,
with a straight man got this on the,
it was my good friend Calvin Trolling,
a straight man who had been on
the Yale Corporation board.
And he finally called up the president
and he said, you really should do this.
And he's really a nice person.
Why don't you meet him again?
And then it went okay from there.
And now there is, which I'm
exceedingly proud of,
the Larry Kramer Initiative for Lesbian
and Gay Studies at Yale, endowed by
my brother, a straight man,
which is going like gangbusters.
What is it?
It's a center for lesbian and gay studies
and they have faculty, they give awards,
there are more speeches sponsored on
campus per year by us than
by any other department,
everybody in the world.
I'm going up next week to introduce
Gore Vidal, who's coming to speak,
to LKI, we call it.
Big deal, Kendall's now
on our board, Kendall Thomas.
Other big people have been asked,
and Kendall is so excited about it.
Anyway, after
all these years, they finally have it.
I mean, mind you,
there's plenty wrong with it.
We're not a department.
We still don't have any tenured faculty,
all that sort of thing.
But it is going like gangbusters.
And LKI is in the papers every 10 minutes.
And I'm, again, so very,
very, very proud of that.
It took me a long time,
because I can remember, as I said,
I'm the kid who tried to kill himself
freshman year because he was gay.
And now there's this.
And I started, as you probably know,
I started an award in honor
of Sarah Pettit for a lesbian,
some kind of lesbian scholarship.
And that's going to happen there
as part of this.
And it's become the center,
an incredible man called Jonathan Katz,
Jonathan David Katz, who runs it.
The art historian?
Yes.
Yeah, okay.
And is this new to you?
Yeah, I'm not,
I'm vaguely aware of it, you know.
Oh, he's come.
I didn't know.
He took, yes, he's gotten Robert Gober
to go up there and talk, and he's doing
a big exhibition on, I forgot,
Lichtenstein, not Lichtenstein,
Rauschenberg,
and He's totally, totally amazing.
I can't remember the name
of that woman, I'll think about it.
Anyway, a lot of people are, have been.
So basically, in terms of
within your class, your position
as a gay man has really been transformed.
That now you're participating in
your class
more fully than you were able to.
What's my class?
Yale, or the, what you said at
the beginning, that regardless of
how many resources you had,
as a gay man you were not seen.
And now they're saying, okay.
So there is a...
Well, I mean, I don't consider
that Yale has welcomed me
into this open arms.
I consider that, you know,
I'm still having fights
with everybody about things.
And we're there...
Yes, they've let us in the door,
but you never should ever feel like you're
welcome forever at the dinner table.
And I feel that way.
But you talked earlier
about people needing people's approval.
And that should never be
a motivating factor.
I threatened to resign
only last week over a fight.
So I am what I am.
And my brother screamed.
You what?
That's your legacy.
I paid for this legacy.
What was the fight?
Was it anything important,
or were you just threatening?
No, it's a principle.
The provost did something behind my back,
and I'm chair of a committee,
and he shouldn't have done it,
and I got very mad.
Larry, I forgot something
I just wanted to ask you, and this is
just a personal question,
but I remember Vito Russo's funeral.
Whose? Vito.
Yeah.
You made this speech
where you said, we killed Vito.
Don't you know that?
Can't you see that?
Mm-hmm.
And I remember feeling
as I was sitting there that I was not
the appropriate target of that speech.
That was just a personal reaction
that I had sitting there.
And I'm wondering if you have had
any hindsight onto that kind
of rhetoric or that sort of approach.
You're too sensitive.
I have tried in
my time many kinds of rhetoric.
You read reports from the Holocaust
and there are many attempts
at different tactics and voices.
Sometimes you need one,
sometimes you need another.
You keep looking.
You make it up as you go along.
When Vito died, everybody was dying
and there still weren't that many people
out there fighting so we did kill veto
and yes you were a tactic
i mean yes you were a target everybody was
a target as many people were in that room
didn't equal the membership of act up
so i
i mean i yell at
gay people still We're all targets.
I still don't do enough.
I get angry at myself because, because,
because, because, because I can't do
all the things I want to do.
Crying at lunch
with Anna all very last week
because I would still like to work with
GMHC.
And she's made
it possible for me to do that.
And I'm going to do it.
And that moves me very much,
that the people are all new,
changed, and they want me back.
But I also know that in doing that,
the novel gets a little short shrifted.
The book, I shouldn't call it
a novel, gets short shrifted.
And that's hard.
I would much rather work in New York
than here, because when David's not here,
I get a little stir crazy.
And so I think, oh,
why can't I go work in New York?
I got a nice apartment and it's quiet
and blah, blah, blah, but the minute
you go back to New York,
you get sucked into
by the electricity of New York.
You want to see Tony, my friend
Tony Kushner, or you want to go see
the play or the movies or whatever,
things that
you somehow manage to keep at bay.
But it happens here, too.
I got to go to Yale and introduce
Gore Vidal next week, and then I agreed.
One of my doctor's nurses is one
of the heads of the American Association
of Nurses with AIDS,
and would I please come
and address their convention?
I have 500 nurses
next week, so I'm going to do that.
And then Judy Falloon says,
would you please come to
this convention at the NIH?
Because all these scientists
have never seen a person like you
I mean all they do is research
they've never seen a person
who's been through what you have
and would you talk to them about that
and of course great that's what I'm
that's my usefulness and all of that
so I have to find
a way of of dealing with all of this.
Tony and I talk about this a lot
because he would much rather be
an activist, he says.
And there's an essay I wrote at the end
of the book, Women and Love, of my stuff,
where he said, well,
you realize that it's not an either or.
You've got to
somehow find a way of doing both.
And fortunately,
you have 20 more years to do it.
From your mouth to somebody's ears.
Thank you, Larry.
Thank you very much.
Thank you.
How long did we go?
We did...